なんば　むった
(南波六太)ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
《ゆうべの無理が
たたったのか…チキショー！》
Guess I pushed myself too hard last night...
Damn!
《ここまで来て
最後の最後に これかよ…！》
This has to happen at the very end?
《情けねぇな～ いつも俺は…》
I always screw up...
On the morning of the sixth,
＜私達 宇宙飛行士候補生
アスキャンが 砂漠７０キロを➡
and final, day of the seventy-kilometer survival training trek by the astronaut candidates or ASCANs,
とうは
踏破するサバイバル訓練
最終日の６日目の朝➡
私は やってしまった…＞
I messed up.
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
(ケンジ)ムッ君…｡
Mu...
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#55 Distant Goal
許されないことをしている相手に
｢許してやろう｣と言える者は➡
When a person is willing to forgive behavior that isn't allowed,
that usually means he hopes for the same exception.
とどのつまり
自分も許してもらいたいのさ｡
I've seen it before.
｢心当たり｣があるからな｡
ハンッ 図星だろ？ビンス｡➡
Isn't that right, Vince?
よう
要は お前がニッタ･レイジに
携帯所持を許したのは➡
In other words, you let Nitta Reiji keep his cell phone
何かお前にも ニッタのような…｡
because you're in a similar situation...
(ビンス)ラリー君｡私は他人の
プライベートにまで➡
Larry,
I simply didn't care to interfere with his personal life.
口出しするつもりがないだけです｡
時間のムダですから｡➡
Because that would be a waste of time.
And there were conditions attached.
それに
ただ許したわけではありません｡➡
He was responsible for handling any problem that might arise.
｢問題が起こった時は
自己責任で解決するように｣➡
という条件での認可です｡
案の定 ニッタは
携帯を一度 紛失し➡
And sure enough, he lost his phone,
ミッションを遅らせ
チームに迷惑をかけましたが…➡
delayed the mission, and caused trouble for his entire team...
ただ…｡
But...
(ラリー)ただ…何よ？
But what?
いや…それより
メールサインが光ってますよ｡
Nothing...
Anyway, your email is flashing.
あらら…サバイバル訓練
最終日だってのに…｡
Oh, man...
And it's the last day of survival training...
(ビンス)何ですか？
What is it?
それでは ここで問題です！
デデンッ！➡
Now, I have a question!
What's happened to Nanba Mutta, of Team E?
現在 Ｅ班のナンバ･ムッタに
何が起こってるでしょう？
ヒントをやろうか？
答えを｡
Want a hint?
Tell me the answer.
(ラリー)ナンバが熱でダウンだ｡
３８度９分だとよ｡
Nanba's come down with a 38.9-degree fever.
Acetaminophen.
アセトアミノフェン…
南波さん 熱を下げる薬です｡
Nanba, this should lower your fever.
あ…はい…｡
O-Okay...
S-Should I consider myself lucky?
《これは…思わぬ幸運…！》
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)皆さん 聞いて下さい｡
Everyone, I have news.
私達Ｅ班 全員リタイアするか➡
In the next five minutes, Team E must decide
それとも 今日中のゴールを
目指して進むか➡
if the entire team will give up or try to reach the goal
５分で決めろって｡
before the day's end.
《リタイア…!?》
Give up?
Give up, huh...?
《リタイアか…正直
休めるもんなら休みてえが…》
Honestly, I'd like to get some rest...
But would it be the right thing to give up in this situation?
《こういう場合の
正しい判断として…➡
リタイアした方がいいのか？》
《俺ひとりのリタイアじゃ
済まねぇ…》
I'm not the only one who'd be affected.
ムッ君 僕らのことを
気にする必要はないよ｡
Mu, you don't need to worry about us.
Thinking long-term,
先のことを考えると 今は
無理しないことも正しい選択だ｡
you shouldn't push yourself too much now.
ケンジ…｡
Kenji...
《だけど もしムッ君が｢進む｣と
判断するなら…➡
But should Mu decide to continue,
僕らは最善を尽くして
ムッ君をフォローしないと！》
we'll do everything we can to help him.
ハハッ サンキュー ケンジ｡
Thanks, Kenji.
でも 俺が決めちゃってい～のか？
今日のリーダーはアマンティだぞ｡
But I don't think that's my decision to make.
Amanti's in charge today.
そうね｡だけど 私の場合
決断するというより➡
True, but in my case,
I already know what the answer will be, Mutta.
｢もう わかってる｣と答えた方が
いいかしらね ムッタ｡
ハァ…ハァ…ハァ…｡
ムッタは歩きます｡
皆さん 出発の準備を！
Mutta will continue walking.
Everyone, let's get ready to go.
さすが…わかってらっしゃる｡
You really are good at that.
南波さん…｡
Nanba...
(ケンジ)よし！急ごう｡
Okay, let's hurry.
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)ムッタ…｡
Mutta...
新田君 何を？
Nitta, what are you doing?
(新田)南波の荷物は
俺が全部持つよ｡当然だ｡
I'll carry Nanba's belongings.
It's only right.
こうなったのは どう考えても
俺に付き合わせたのが原因だ｡
He probably got sick because he helped me out.
《え…？》
Huh?
そこは僕も
協力させてくれよ 新田君｡
Let me help you, Nitta.
私も持ちます｡
(北村)私も 私も｡
I can also help.
Me, too!
Wow, everyone!
《おおっ 皆さんっ！》
わかった…
かつ
だが 半分は俺に担がせてくれ｡➡
Fine.
But I'm taking half of it.
You guys can split the rest.
残り半分は
みんなで分けてくれりゃいい｡
ＯＫ それでいこう｡
Okay, we'll go with that.
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)さあ 出発よ ムッタ｡
Let's get going, Mutta.
大丈夫 必ずゴールできます｡
Don't worry.
I promise we'll reach the goal.
《ありがてえ～！》
I feel so grateful!
《この ありがたさが力になる…》
And these feelings of gratitude are giving me strength.
It doesn't matter if we place last,
《最下位でも何でもいいから絶対
ゴールまで歩いてやる…》
as long as I walk all the way to the goal.
《１位と最下位との差なんて
大したことね～んだよ》
Not all that much separates the first and last places.
《ゴールすることと
しないことの差に比べりゃ！》
Not as compared to finishing or not finishing.
まだか？遅えな アイツら｡
What's taking so long?
They're really slow.
Here they come.
来たよ みんな立派だ｡
They're so strong!
《ハァ…もうすぐだ…！》
We're almost there...
Mutta...
《ムッタ…熱があるのに
頑張りすぎだよ…》
You shouldn't push yourself so hard while you're sick!
《なんて…
サムライスピリッツだ…》
This is the spirit of a samurai!
ハァ…ハァ…｡
ムッタ…｡
Mutta!
(ﾛｰﾘｰ)《手助けはできないが…➡
I can't help you directly...
But I hope this Japanese word will give you the strength to finish!
せめて この日本語を見て
最後の力を ふり絞ってほしい…》
どした？ローリー｡
What's up, Lowry?
君に贈ろう 僕の大切な言葉…➡
Here is the word I have for you!
イッツ…➡
プライド！
It's "pride"!
そうきたか…｡
So that's what you were up to.
ゴミのようなプライドだな｡
Pride that the wind can blow away.
ありがとよ ローリー｡
Thanks, Lowry.
ドウ…イタシマシテ…｡
You're welcome.
ゴールが見えてきたわ！
もうすぐです 皆さん｡
The goal's within sight.
We're almost there, everyone.
Great!
(ケンジ)よっしゃあ！
やった～！
(北村)長かったぁ…！
Yay!
That was a long hike.
《着いた…やっと着いた…
これでようやく 次の訓練に…》
We made it...
We finally made it...
At last, we can move on to the next stage of training...
What?
なんだ…？
《なんだこりゃ…!?》
What is that?
(技術者)お～い ピコ｡➡
Hey, Pico.
今度はＢ班が到着したってよ｡
Team B has arrived.
面会に行きましょう ピコさん｡
We should go meet them, Pico.
(技術者)だめだ また寝てるよ｡
｢ぐうたらピコ｣｡
Forget it... He's asleep again.
That guy's so damned lazy.
(ピコ)おい！いくら俺でも➡
Hey...
It's physically impossible for me to fall asleep sitting like this, you morons.
たいせい
こんな体勢で寝れるわけねえだろ
クソバカどもが！
なんだ 起きてた｡
Oh, you're awake?
行きましょう ピコさん｡
次あたり 選ばれますよ｡
Come on, Pico.
You might be chosen this time.
(ピコ)フッ 俺なんか…｡
ふあああ～あ～…➡
You think so?
アホかね 君らは｡
俺を担当に指名するような➡
How stupid can you be?
If any ASCAN actually chose to be assigned to me,
アスキャンがいたとしたら
てんねんきねんぶつ
そいつは天然記念物だぜ｡
it'd be one hell of an oddball.
あっ！ちっ クソが～｡
Damn...
きが
(ｻﾞｯｸ)着替え終わりました｡
３位で到着したＢ班代表➡
We've finished changing.
From Team B, which placed third, Zack McConnell...
ザック･マコンネルと…｡
(ｼﾞｬｯｸ)ジャック･ジョンソンです｡
...and Jack Johnson.
さばく
ＯＫ～ 砂漠の旅 お疲れさま｡
ずのうせん
こっからは頭脳戦だ｡
Okay, congrats on making it through the desert.
Now it's time to use your brains.
説明しよう｡
Let me explain.
君達にやってもらうのは これだ｡
This is your next task.
Next, you will be participating in the 26th Comeback Competition.
くんれん
次の訓練は
第２６回ｶﾑﾊﾞｯｸｺﾝﾍﾟﾃｨｼｮﾝに➡
さんせん
参戦することだ｡ハンッ｡
かいさい
これは 昔から開催されてる➡
This is a CanSat contest that's held for students who love space.
宇宙好きの学生達が参加する
キャンサットの打ち上げ大会だ｡➡
キャンサットには
きそ
宇宙開発に必要な技術基礎が➡
CanSats use all kinds of technology required for space exploration.
ぜ～んぶ詰まってる｡
ミッションはこうだ｡➡
Here is your mission.
ほうしゅつ
ロケットから空中で放出された
キャンサットを➡
After your CanSat is launched by airborne rocket, it must parachute to the ground,
ちゃくち
パラシュートで着地させ
きどう
ローバーを起動｡➡
then deploy a rover.
じどうせいぎょ
自動制御でゴールフラッグに
向かわせ 着地点から➡
The automated rover must navigate to the goal flag.
You'll be judged on distance covered and time spent in travel.
フラッグまでの距離と
かかった時間を競う｡
正直 簡単じゃないぜ｡
Honestly, it isn't very easy.
ロケットだけは 全ての班に
同じものをこちらで用意してある｡
We'll provide each team with the same rocket.
今回 君らが作るのは
キャンサット｡➡
You will be building the CanSat,
パラシュートの展開システムから
自動制御で動くローバーまでだ｡➡
parachute deployment system, and the automated rover.
２週間後の大会に出場して
他の班や 学生達と➡
Over two weeks, you'll compete against the other teams and various students.
順位を競ってもらう｡
なるほど｡
I see.
２週間もあるなら 今日はもう
休んでもよさそうだな｡
If we have two weeks, we can take today off.
Yeah.
ハンッ まあそのへんの判断は
君らに任せるが➡
Well, that's your decision to make, of course...
３位の君らが
ゆうちょう
かま
そんな悠長な構えで大丈夫かい？
But remember that you're in third place.
The first-place Team A is already at work.
(ラリー)１位で到着したＡ班は
もう準備を始めてるぜ｡
《なんだこりゃ!?》
What is that?
≪ヘェ～イ！≫
Hey!
あれは Ａ班の…｡
He's from Team A.
(ケンジ)シェイン達だ｡
It's Shane and his team.
かだい
このローバーが 次の課題？
This rover is our next task?
どういうことですか？
What do you mean?
あんたらラッキーだぜ｡➡
You guys lucked out, getting to see this.
こいつの作動するところを
見れて｡ヘヘッ｡➡
俺達Ａ班も 今初めて
よしゅう
見たところだ 予習としてな｡
It's our first time getting to see an example of a rover in action.
An example?
(ケンジ)予習？
This rover was created by Eric, the engineer who will support Team A, while he was still a student.
このローバーは Ａ班の
サポート役になってもらった➡
技術者 エリック君が
学生の頃に作ったものだ｡
(エリック)はい～｡
(シｪイン)５人いる技術者の中で➡
Yes...
Eric was the only one out of the five engineers who had an actual rover.
ローバーの実物を持っていたのは
エリック君だけだった｡➡
彼は去年 このカムバックコンペに
出場したから➡
He participated in last year's Comeback Competition, so he knows his stuff.
ちしき
ほうふ
しんせん
知識だって豊富で新鮮｡
まよ
だから迷わず最年少の
エリｯク君を担当に選んだんだよ➡
That's why we immediately chose to be assigned the youngest engineer, Eric.
勝つためにね｡
To help us win.
I see...
なるほど…５人の技術者から
サポート役を選べるんだ｡
So we'll select one of five engineers to support us.
(シェイン)そういうこった｡
There you go.
Unfortunately, you probably won't have a choice.
残念だが おそらく
あんたらに選べる権利はない｡
(ベン)技術者を選べるのは➡
Eh?
The teams pick in the order of their survival training finish.
サバイバル訓練のゴール順だ｡
最下位のキミ達Ｅ班は➡
Since Team E came in last, you'll be stuck with whoever is left over.
つか
当然 残り物を掴まされる｡
Why am I here?
Now choose of these engineers.
さあ この中から１人選んでくれ｡
あ…ふぁ～ あ～…｡
ガム食う？
いいや｡
Want some gum?
No.
あっ そう｡
Okay, then.
あん｡クチャクチャ…｡
ねいき
一番右のヤツ以外なら
どっちでもいいぜ｡
I'm good with anyone other than the guy on the right.
I agree.
どうかん
(ジャック)同感｡
(候補生)私も｡
Ditto.
クァ～…カァ～…｡
Okay...
さて お前らか
はめ
俺と組む羽目になった➡
So you're the hopeless team that finished last and was stuck with me?
ど～しようもねえ最下位チームは｡
そう…です｡
That's right...
フッ おめでとう
ある意味 おめでとう｡➡
Congratulations.
Actually, you should be happy.
全５班の中で君らが一番自由だぜ｡
自由気ままにやってくれ｡
Because you'll have more freedom than the other teams.
You can do whatever the hell you want.
俺のスイッチは
今 オフなんでな｡➡
At the moment, my switch is flipped to "off".
I won't say a word or lift a finger.
口も出さねえし
手も出すつもりは ねえよ｡
《なんとっ》
What's that?
You see...
俺はな…｡
俺は君らが ど～なろうと
知ったこっちゃねえし｡
I really don't give a damn how you do.
ヘッ それこそ 屁でもねえ｡
I don't give a damn fart.
《屁は…出すんだ》
But you did fart...
(ピコ)このコンペに参加する
他の学生達は➡
The student participants in this contest have been preparing for six months.
半年も前から準備してきてる｡
初心者のアスキャン軍団が➡
It's impossible for a bunch of novice ASCANs to build something in two weeks that has any chance to win.
たった２週間で勝てるモノを
作れるワケがねえんだよ｡
That's why my switch stays off.
俺のスイッチが
入んねえ理由は そこだ｡➡
Life is too short, and I don't have time to waste on lost causes.
いつ終わってもおかしくない
人生の中で➡
テンションの上がらねえことに
パワー使いたくないぜ｡
あれ？
どこ行くですか ピコさん？
Wait, where are you going, Pico?
帰んだよ｡
飲みに行く約束があんの｡
I'm leaving...
I'm supposed to go drinking with someone.
《なんてこった…
サポート役の人が➡
I don't believe it...
We aren't getting any support from the engineer who's supposed to support us.
サポートして
じたい
くれないという事態｡➡
だけど 作るモノはローバーだ》
But we'll be building a rover...
とくいぶんや
《車関係なら俺の得意分野｡➡
I'm good with vehicles.
逆転のチャ～ンス！》
This is our chance for a comeback.
少し熱下がってます 南波さん！
Your fever's gone down a bit, Nanba.
今日ゆっくり休めば
明日から復活ですよ｡
If you get plenty of rest tonight, you should be back in action tomorrow.
あ ありがとう せりかさん｡
Thank you, Serika...
もとじょい
《さすが元女医さんだ｡
誰かが病気とかしたら➡
You can tell she used to be a doctor.
She volunteers to care for the sick.
みずか
かいほう
自らすすんで介抱してくれる》
《ちょっと待て！
その手があったか！》
Hold on!
I can use that!
⦅せりかさん
なんか急にお腹が…⦆
Serika, my stomach hurts...
Are you okay, Nanba?
⦅大丈夫ですか？南波さん
服 脱いでください⦆
Please remove your shirt.
《ムフ…フフフ…》
Are you okay, Mu?
(ケンジ)ムッ君 大丈夫？
じゃあ お休み ムッ君｡
(北村)また明日ね｡
Good night, Mu.
See you tomorrow.
あ おやすみ｡ありがとう｡
Good night... Thank you.
おやすみ ムッタ｡
Good night, Mutta.
あっ アマンティ ちょっと…｡
Amanti, hold on.
うら
初めて俺を占った時
ふおん
ちょっと 不穏な顔したろ？
When you told my fortune the first time we met,
you looked a little upset...
あれって
この熱のことだったんだな｡
Was it because you knew I'd come down with a fever?
え ええ…そうね その通りよ｡
Y-Yes, indeed...
That's right.
(ｱﾏﾝﾃｨ)おやすみなさい｡
Good night.
I helped a teammate find his cell phone.
《仲間の携帯を探し歩いたり
発熱してみんなに助けられたり➡
Then the group helped me out, after I caught a fever.
教える気ゼロなうえに 屁こきの
技術者が担当についたり…》
Then we got stuck with an engineer who didn't want to help at all...
《なかなか いろいろ
ひびと
あるもんだな 日々人｡➡
A lot can happen, Hibito...
お前もこんな訓練を乗り越えて
今 そこにいるんだな》
You were able to overcome this training, to make it up there.
I can't wait to get there.
《早く俺も行きたいぜ…》
(ピコ)ヘイ ビンス｡
Hey, Vince.
(客)あの子 カワイかったな｡
She was cute.
You know, seriously...
(客)もしかして お前さ～…｡
(客)なんだよ｡
What now?
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
Who is this Pico guy?
＜ピコって 一体 何モンだ!?
話を聞くうち➡
After asking around, it turns out Pico once held an important NASA post.
ピコは 宇宙開発の ある意外な
ポジションにいたことが わかる＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
#56 A Promise Over a Drink
"A Promise Over a Drink"
There's only one thing I want to do.
＜俺が本当にやりたい事ってのは
１つしかないんだ＞